<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A relation of the victory of Elvas obtained over the Spaniard, by the Army of the high and mighty Prince Alfonso the sixth King of  Portugal, upon the 14th of January, 1659.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 79KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B09867</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">64551673</idno>
  <idno type="VID">184759</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240884694</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing R889A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R182600</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">64551673</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B09867)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 184759)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2871:25)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A relation of the victory of Elvas obtained over the Spaniard, by the Army of the high and mighty Prince Alfonso the sixth King of  Portugal, upon the 14th of January, 1659.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 24, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Roger Norton,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Translated out of the original Portugues by an English gentleman."</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: pages cropped with some loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Linhas de Elvas, Battle of, Elvas, Portugal, 1659 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:184759:1"/>
            <p>A RELATION Of the VICTORY OF ELVAS Obtained over the <hi>SPANIARD,</hi> By <hi>The Army of the High and Mighty Prince</hi> ALFONSO <hi>the Sixth King of</hi> Portugal, <hi>upon the</hi> 14<seg rend="sup">th</seg>
               <hi>of</hi> January, 1659.</p>
            <p>Translated out of the Original <hi>Portugues</hi> by an English Gentleman.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>ROGER NORTON,</hi> 1661.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:184759:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:184759:2"/>
            <head>PREFACE OF THE TRANSLATOR.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He great entertainment I have had in reading the Atchievements of the <hi>Portugues</hi> in the field of <hi>Elvas,</hi> makes me believe, that it may be grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to others to read them too, and that an acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on worthy to be celebrated in all Languages should not be confined to one. For this reason I have adventured to English this relation of the Seige of <hi>Elvas,</hi> and to presenr it to my Countrey, wherein I doubt not but there are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny who will be concern'd in the successes of so just a cause, and so renowned a Nation.</p>
            <p>It is a common interest that the States of Europe have in the defence of <hi>Portugal,</hi> but there are some more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular considerations which oblige the English to desire her conservation. I Will not speak of the ancient confedera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies betwixt the Nations, nor of that famous allyance with <hi>England,</hi> from whence the most illustrious families of <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugal</hi> are descended. I need not mention (though it must never be forgotten) the late affection which the <hi>Portugues</hi> shewed to the English name in owning our Lord the KING in the lowest of his fortunes, and when the power of his Enemies was most prevailing, in entring into a War to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect his Fleet at a time that they had so much business to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend themselves, and were in a condition fitter to receive
<pb facs="tcp:184759:3"/> assistance than to give it. And, which added mightily to the glory of the action, in doing this when the greatest Monarchs of Christendome, who were nearer to him, were courting his Rebels, and contending for their favour. But to pass over the memory of former Obligations which sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie so little amongst States compared with the respects of present advantage, that which I mean engageth us to be concerned for <hi>Portugal,</hi> is the mighty use we may make of her amity, as she is a separate Estate from <hi>Spaine,</hi> and the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>incidence of interest which is betwixt us.</p>
            <p>It is now the jealousie of all our Potent Neighbours that <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Portugal</hi> will be united in one interest. The <hi>Spaniard</hi> apprehends it as a thing destructive to their Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy; the <hi>Hollander</hi> as that which will hinder them from engrossing the Trade of the world, and the <hi>French</hi> it may be are not pleased with it for several reasons. Indeed it is no wonder if Nations which are emulous of our greatness should be against a business which will bring us such an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cession of strength and riches, as will make us Masters of the Navigation of both the <hi>Indies,</hi> give us retreats and footing in <hi>Africa, Persia, China, Brasile,</hi> and consequently, erect a third interest in Christendome, which may subsist of it self, and be no way dependent either upon the House of <hi>France</hi> or <hi>Austria.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Composer of this Relation (Reader) hath not thought fit to put his name before it. But whoever he was, he seems to me to have been transported with a noble zeal for the glory of his Countrey, and warmed with the joys of victory when he writ it. And you will finde by the dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of the stile, the choiseness of the words, and the whole manner of the thing however it appear disfigured in my English, that it was not done by any vulgar hand.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:184759:3"/>
            <head>A RELATION Of the <hi>BATTAIL</hi> OF ELVAS.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE unseasonable death of King <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hn</hi> the fourth of happy memory, whom Heaven had miraculously restored to the usurped Scepter of the <hi>Portuguais</hi> Monarchy, encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged the Arms of <hi>Spain</hi> to try the fortune of war in the minority of the new King <hi>Alfonso</hi> the sixth.</p>
            <p>In order to this end, in the beginning of the year 1657. D. <hi>Francisco Tutavila</hi> Duke of St. <hi>Germane</hi> set out of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dajos</hi> with 12000 Foot and 4000 Horse against the Town of <hi>Olivenza,</hi> and notwithstanding the vigilant care of the Queen Regent in sending a brave army to succour that place, (rather by fate and the favour of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, then by any act of valour or military order) he became master of it, and in a few dayes the town of <hi>Mouram</hi> yielded to him too, having first bravely defended it self.</p>
            <p>With these successes the Armies of <hi>Spain</hi> retired triumphant, making known to the Nations of Europe a secret not till then discovered, that in the military contentions of those two Crowns the <hi>Portugueses</hi> could be conquered. But the contentment of this victory lasted not many dayes, for in the Autumn of the same year the Army of <hi>Portugal</hi> under the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of <hi>John Mendes de Vasconcellos</hi> Lieutenant Geneneral of <hi>Alentejo</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered the town of <hi>Mouram,</hi> but with this difference in the case, that now it was garrison'd with souldiers it was won in three dayes, which having none before but the people of the Countrey in it, had resisted ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:184759:4"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Portugal</hi> was now deprived of the satisfaction of <hi>Olivenza,</hi> and though the taking of <hi>Albuquerque</hi> or <hi>Valenza</hi> had been a sufficient compensation for it, such was the bravery of the <hi>Portugues</hi> that they could not be content to proportion their revenge to their loss, but aspiring generously to some greater enterprize, the 12. of <hi>June</hi> in the year of our Lord 1658. the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of <hi>Portugal</hi> sate down before <hi>Badajos</hi> the place and magazine of Arms of the Kingdome of <hi>Castile.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It would be for the credit of <hi>Portugal</hi> here to relate those glorious feats of Arms which were atchieved in the course of their seige, as well in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vesting and storming the Fort of St. <hi>Christopher,</hi> as in the obstinate battail and glorious victory which preceded the taking of Fort St. <hi>Michael.</hi> But as these successes are committed to the care of another Pen, which will shortly make them publick, and my business is confin'd only to the suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cess of the succour of <hi>Elvas,</hi> it will not be for me to intrench upon the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of another, nor to exceed the limits of my undertaking.</p>
            <p>The enterprize of <hi>Badajos</hi> went to the heart of the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> who was highly offended that the world should see at this time his place of Arms beseiged, a chance which till then had not happened to him in any part of Europe. And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e resentment thereof was so deep, that he recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended the succouring of it to his favourite <hi>Don Luis de Haro.</hi> So great was the umbrage that Kingdome took, though there be so much hazard in the absence of a favourite from his Prince, that <hi>Don Luis</hi> resolved he would be the first should leave the King in this occasion.</p>
            <p>He began then to call together the Nobility of <hi>Spain,</hi> and the preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to Court, some out of flattery, and others out of dependence, drew presently together, and making many levies through those Kingdomes, their forces arrived at <hi>Merida Albuquerque</hi> and <hi>Olivenza.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At this time the Arms of <hi>Portugal</hi> with an obstinate seige of four moneths had reduced <hi>Badajos</hi> to the last gasp. When Heaven fighting in favour of the beseiged afflicted the beseigers with so many and so grievous diseases, that besides the chief Captains who retired to <hi>Elvas</hi> in that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity, there dyed 600 officers through the same occasion, the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the common souldiers who were sick amounting to twelve thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand.</p>
            <p>Some Armies, that had been deprived of so many vital spirits, would have left off the seige in disorder, not like this Nation, who with invin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible constancy shewed it possible to live by the river of <hi>Guadiana</hi> in the heat of the Dog-dayes. But the publick calamity every day encreasing, though their generous ambition would not have let them lose that glory which they had now almost in their hands, it was unanimously resolved
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:184759:4"/> by all the Captains to save the remainder of the Army, which was done the twelfth of <hi>October,</hi> but with so much bravery and good order, that in the judgement of the skilful in the art of war, <hi>Portugal</hi> might make as much account of that retreat, as she could have done of the greatest victory.</p>
            <p>There were now remaining in the fields of <hi>Badajos</hi> no other marks of the siege, then the Trenches which were made in the earth, and the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kases which had perished by the sword of the <hi>Portugues.</hi> The Besiegers carryed all away with them, with too scrupulous a care, that they even set fire to a little Boat which was broken in their march, that it might not be taken. And so retired in great quiet, the Spanish Army not da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to hinder them, or so much as embarasse their retreat. But as soon as our army was retired, the Auxiliaries discharged to refresh them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves after so long a siege, the Regiments and Troops sent into Garrison to <hi>Campo Major, Villa vitiosa, Borba, Estremoz, Arroches</hi> and <hi>Monforte,</hi> and that the power of <hi>Portugal</hi> was weakned by this division, the <hi>Spanish</hi> ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my upon the fifteenth of <hi>October</hi> appeared in the field, and passing over the River of <hi>Caya,</hi> marched thorough the Plains of <hi>Portugal.</hi> The <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish</hi> army consisted of Fourteen thousand foot, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d Five thousand horse, of which <hi>Don Luis de Haro</hi> Marquess of <hi>Carpio,</hi> Count and Duke of <hi>Oliva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rez,</hi> Favourite to the King, Master of the Horse, and great Chancellor of the East Indies, was Captain General. The Government of Arms was committed to the charge of <hi>Francis Tutavila</hi> Duke of Saint <hi>German. D. Rodrigo Muxica</hi> was Camp-master General, the Duke of <hi>Ossuna</hi> Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral of the Horse, <hi>Don Gasper de la Cueva</hi> brother to the Duke of <hi>Albu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querque</hi> and <hi>D. Ventura Tarragona</hi> Generals of the Artillery, the one in the exercise, the other in the title, who had besides the Office of Engineer Major. <hi>D. John Pacheco</hi> was Lievtenant General of the Horse.</p>
            <p>The Colonels, and the Captains of Horse and Foot, were chosen ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther out of the best Nobility, or those who had done the most deserving services. So that in the Regiments as well as the Troops there served many <hi>Titulati,</hi> many sons, brothers, and kinsmen of the best Houses of <hi>Spain,</hi> which were inforced with Four thousand Reformado-officers, a strength sufficient to conquer an ample Monarchy.</p>
            <p>With this Army so formidable both for number and quality, <hi>Don Luis de Haro</hi> marched to the Fountain of <hi>Sapateiros</hi> betwixt <hi>Elvas</hi> and <hi>Estremos,</hi> and being able to atchieve greater matters, considering the condition in which the County was, contented himself with the slight enterprizes of <hi>Villaboim, Barbacenu,</hi> and <hi>Sancta Olaya,</hi> places so little and of such small importance, that they served onely to discredit the reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:184759:5"/> of his Arms, since having his free election of so many populous Towns as were near his Army, he employed it onely upon such, as for the inconsiderable number of the Inhabitants were not able to defend themselves.</p>
            <p>At this time the City of <hi>Elvas</hi> was in so miserable a condition, that it seemed rather an Hospital, then a Town, that had either Inhabitants or Souldiers. The great Officers all sick to extremity, excepting <hi>Mendes de Vasconcellos,</hi> and <hi>D. Sancho Manuel</hi> Camp-master General and Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of the Province of <hi>Beira,</hi> who was come from the Town of <hi>Penamo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cor</hi> to give life to the siege of <hi>Badajos,</hi> and exercise the office of Camp-master General, arriving there the same day that the Army retired. <hi>D. Rodrigo de Castro</hi> Count of <hi>Mesquitela</hi> was gone away before, almost despairing of his life, to the town of <hi>Montemor.</hi> The Regiments, some were without Colonels, or the Colonels without Regiments. The Troops and Companies without Captains, or the Captains without Troops and Companies. They who were in health so toil'd and harassed with a long siege, that they were scarce to be distinguished from the sick, the town destitute of all necessary provisions, since being the next place to <hi>Badajos,</hi> it wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>otally exhausted with supplying the Army du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the siege.</p>
            <p>This was the condition of the City of <hi>Elvas,</hi> which besides this cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity was afflicted with another as great, and that was from the conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration that all they had was in this place. For here were all the great Officers, <hi>John Mendes de Vasconcellos, Andrew Albuquerque</hi> Camp-master General, and General of the Horse, <hi>D. Sancho Manoel</hi> Campmaster Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, and <hi>Alfonso Furtado de Mendosa</hi> General of the Artillery, <hi>Peter James Magellan</hi> General too of the Artillery, &amp; who had been General of the Fleet of <hi>Brasile, D. Francisco de Sousa</hi> Count of <hi>Prado,</hi> of his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties Councel of War, and Governour of this Town and Province during the siege of <hi>Badajos, Fernando de Silveyra</hi> of the Councel of War, and Admiral of the Navy Royal, <hi>D. Luis Almeida,</hi> who had been Governor of the River of <hi>Janeiro</hi> in the State of <hi>Brasile,</hi> and who was to be Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of this town in case the Count of <hi>Prado</hi> should be disabled by sickness.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Elvas</hi> also were these Colonels <hi>Diego Gomes de Figueiredo</hi> Campma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster of the Army Royal, <hi>John Leite d' Oliveira, Augustin Andrada, Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Correa da Silva, Luis Alvares de Tauora</hi> Count of Saint <hi>John, Diego de Mendosa Furtado</hi> of payd Regiments, and <hi>Bernardino de Siqueira, Antonio de Sa de Menezes,</hi> and <hi>Manoel de Sousa de Castro</hi> of Auxiliaries, <hi>Fran. Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>checo Mascarenhas</hi> and <hi>Don John Mascarenhas</hi> Count of <hi>Torre,</hi> whose men
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:184759:5"/> were in garrison in other towns, they themselves being detain'd here by sickness, whose forces joyned together made up the number of five or six thousand foot. In this place also were the Lieutenant Generals of the <hi>Cavalry, Achim de Tamaricurt, Manoel, Freire d' Andrada,</hi> and <hi>Gil Vas Lobo</hi> with 1500 horse, who in the first moneth of the seige at several sallies got out of the town, leaving behind them in it <hi>D. John de Silva</hi> Commissary General with 200 horse.</p>
            <p>Here were likewise all the provisions which had been sav'd with the Army, which was all that this Province in so long a seige could supply it with, here was the train of Artillery, the Tents, and all the baggage of an Army; and lastly, though there were not much in the place, all was there that was in the Countrey.</p>
            <p>This information coming from all parts animated the Spanish Army to the resolution of beseiging <hi>Elvas,</hi> as being confident that the place had neither force within to defend it self, nor the Kingdome to relieve it, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving brought into the field, in less then a year and half, three numerous Armies only of one Nation, the last of which had been totally dissipated by sickness, and that it would now be difficult to draw together the men that had been disbanded, in regard they had bee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> so wearied with the inconveniences of the long seige of <hi>Badajos,</hi> and that the royal patrimony must have been exhausted with the vast and continued charge of three Armies. <hi>Elvas</hi> is the second City of the Province of <hi>Alentejo,</hi> and the first that devides the Kingdomes of <hi>Portugal</hi> and <hi>Castile,</hi> distant the space of three leagues from the City of <hi>Badajos,</hi> and the chiefe place of Arms of <hi>Portugal.</hi> It consists of some three thousand inhabitants, and is an Episco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Sea, the Peasants are rich, and the Countrey about it covered with Vines and Olives, and many pleasant gardens which serve both for the use and delight of the inhabitants. It is situated on the side of a hill, upon which there is a Castle which eminently overlooks a deep valley. About it are five small hills, <hi>Casarano,</hi> St. <hi>Lucy,</hi> St. <hi>Peter,</hi> and St. <hi>Francis,</hi> which are all near, and our Lady of grace which lies at more distance. The two first were fortified with out-works, that of St. <hi>Lucy</hi> with four Bulwarks and some ravelines, and that of <hi>Casarano</hi> with a crown; both of them having communication with the town by cover'd wayes.</p>
            <p>The hills of <hi>St. Francis</hi> and <hi>St. Peter</hi> were not at all fortified, the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my possessing themselves of the first the first day that they sate down be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the town, and it was thought fit to fortifie the second after the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the seige. Our Lady of Grace, though the most eminent of them all above the Castle was excused from being fortified by reason of the distance. Betwixt these hills run two little rivers by the inhabitants
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:184759:6"/> called <hi>Chinches</hi> and <hi>Seto,</hi> which in a little space empty themselves into the <hi>Caya,</hi> and with it into the river of <hi>Guadiana.</hi> The town was anciently wall'd according to the necessity of those times, but of late fortified with Curtaines, Bulwarks, and half Bulwarks, encompassed with a broad and deep ditch, with divers ravelines, half-moons, and cover'd waygal ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodated to the irregularity of the situation, and according to the precepts of modern fortification. The situation does much assist the art of the fortification, being disposed in that manner, that from the irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularity of the place there arise so many sorts of defence, that there is no part of the circumference which hath not many batteries, and is not flank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with bulwarks, walls and out-works, which are further strengthened by the nature of the situation, as being founded upon a rock, with little earth in the superficies, which made the approaches difficult, the ditch being also cut in the quick rock, all which together makes it one of the strongest and best places of Europe.</p>
            <p>The 22. of <hi>October</hi> in the morning, the Spanish army appeared before the Monastery of St. <hi>Francis,</hi> that solitary and religious habitation of the Capuchin Friars of the Province of <hi>Piedade,</hi> distant from the town about musquet shot. In w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ch place lay sick in the last period of his life the Count of <hi>Penaguiano,</hi> who was great Chamberlain to his Majestie, his Councellor of state and war, and had been Ambassador extraordinary to the Commonwealth of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Christian modesty obligeth me not to mention the insolencies that were committed against those sacred walls, the indecencies done to those religious persons which inhabited them, the confusion and darkness of the night would not let them take notice of what piety and reverence ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged them to. And yet I can not deny, but that the Count being in that condition, they had no natural compassion for him, imprisoning a car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kass rather then a man, for in a few houres after his imprisonment he dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, adding honour by the circumstances of his death to those great ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices which he had rendred his Prince when he was living. Upon the first noise of this <hi>Mendes de Vasconcellos</hi> sent <hi>Gomes de Figuiredo</hi> with a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to be ascertained of the truth of this rumour, and then <hi>Simon Correa da Silva</hi> with another, who skirmish'd all day with that part of the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies army, which had taken up their quarters in the Monastery, driving one another out twice, so that on both sides they received great loss, till the approach of night parted the combate, the enemy making good the post.</p>
            <p>The 14/24. of <hi>October</hi> arriv'd at <hi>Lisbone</hi> the newes of the enemies intent, and of the seige of <hi>Elvas,</hi> and though there were some reason to deject
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:184759:6"/> their hopes considering the state of the Kingdome, they were rais'd with the consideration of the justice of their cause, and the rare prudence and restless activity of the Queen Regent, who took such care for the preser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of her Kingdomes, and the defence of her subjects. It was then, that desiring to provide a convenient remedy for the occurring mischief, in which there was such need of some person of great courage and high fidelity, she call'd for the Count of <hi>Cantanhede D. Luis de Meneses</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor of state and war, and Governour of <hi>Cascais,</hi> and after she had represented to him the importance of the business, nominated him for the imployment.</p>
            <p>The reasons with which the Queen perswaded the Count to undertake this expedition as they passed only betwixt her Majesty and the Count are not come to publick knowledge. It is probable that to the zeal of the Count it was enough that the business concerned the good of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and that for the same reason that the expedition was so highly ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zardous, he was the more willing to accept it, it being a quality insepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable from valour to love danger. It may be the reasons that prevailed with him are the same as are contain'd in the letter which the Queen was pleas'd to write to him, of which I have here set down a copy for the publick curiosity.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>CONDE my friend, I the King send you greeting as to him I love. It being of so much importance to send into the Province of <hi>Alentejo</hi> to govern there during the continuance of the Enemy before <hi>Elvas,</hi> some such person as may ease and comfort the People, and be of authority capable to raise an Army to succour the place if necessity require, though for the importance of your person I cannot be without you, I am feigne to command you to set out presently to deliver me from the care, which the affairs of that Province give me, and to render me and those Kingdomes so great a service as that will be. And because with one who bears such an affection to me and to the Kingdome, and so much desires its conservation and defence, a few words will prevail to undertake the business, upon the receipt of these few lines I hope you will depart, and by these I command all Chiefs and Officers of War and Justice, and that they fulfil and keep your orders in all that shall concern the forementioned business, wherein I hope you will behave your self according to your quality and the good affection that I have for you, which must needs be two powerful incitations to such a man as you.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Written at <hi>Lisbone</hi>
                        <date>the <hi>2<seg rend="sup">d</seg>.</hi> of <hi>November,</hi> in the year <hi>1658.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>The QUEEN.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:184759:7"/>
            <p>To the commands of Kings, especially when they respect the publick good, ready execution is the best answer. The Count as he was obliged by obedience and publick necessity, forthwith provided what was impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant for his journey. The 20. of <hi>November</hi> he departed from the Court and arrived at <hi>Estremos</hi> the 24<seg rend="sup">th</seg>. where the general acclamations where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he was received in that Province, was the first presage of victory, and a certain Prognostication, that he was the person to whom they were to owe their quiet security.</p>
            <p>The order of writing requires that I should give account of the arrival of the Count at <hi>Estremos</hi> before I speak of the sally which was made out of <hi>Elvas</hi> by <hi>Andrew Albuquerque</hi> camp-Master General, and <hi>Alfonso Furtado de Mendosa</hi> General of the Artillery, who being commanded out of <hi>Elvas,</hi> by reason of the want there was of Officers for the new Army, resolved to make their way through the midst of the Enemies quarters, leaving <hi>D. Sancho Manuel</hi> behind them to be governour of the town. They sallied the 14. of <hi>November</hi> accompanied only with a hundred horse, amongst whom were the chief Captains of the Army and Officers of the Treasury, and with their swords in their hands opened their way in such manner, that they got the same day to <hi>Estremos,</hi> leaving their enemies more busied in admiring, then in hindring of them.</p>
            <p>There was not at this time in all the garrisons of the Countrey above two thousand paid Foot and 1800 Horse, both of them harassed out with the continual service of the long seige of <hi>Badajos.</hi> The train of Artillery was in <hi>Elvas</hi> and the munition. The Kingdome was mightily exhausted of men, for besides those who were lost in service and wasted in the past <hi>Campania</hi>'s, it had supplied for four moneths continually the seige of <hi>Bada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jos</hi> with new men, the greater part of which were consumed with sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, and the rest made unserviceable. And since in the Armies of <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugal</hi> there is no other Nation serves but the <hi>Portugues,</hi> it was so, that when the Count went to raise a new Army, it seemed a greater business to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take, then he found it was to effect it.</p>
            <p>At this time the Enemy made good about the town fix quarters, the <hi>Bargada</hi> which lay towards <hi>Campo major, la Courte</hi> betwixt the fountain <hi>dos Ferradores</hi> and the valley of <hi>Revelles</hi> in the way from <hi>Atalaya,</hi> the val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley of <hi>Marmelo,</hi> which fronted <hi>Atalaya,</hi> the quarter of <hi>Cosena</hi> which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan in the way of <hi>Villa boim,</hi> and extended to the fifth in the Covent of the <hi>Franciscans,</hi> the sixth upon the top of our Lady of Grace.</p>
            <p>All these quarters were strongly fortified, and lines of circumvallati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons made with Forts at proportionate distances, all of them wrought ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:184759:7"/> to art. The best amongst them, and that which had given the Enemy the greatest thought, was the fortification of the valley of <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melo,</hi> and that of <hi>la Corte,</hi> which were close together, being affraid of that side towards <hi>Villa vitiosa,</hi> from whence according to their intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence there was a designe to introduce succour.</p>
            <p>The quarter of <hi>Bargada</hi> was committed to the charge of <hi>Don Ventura Tarragona</hi> General of the Artillery, in which was lodged the greatest part of the <hi>Cavalry.</hi> In the quarter of <hi>la Corte</hi> (which was governed by the Duke of St. <hi>German</hi>) lay their best regiments of Foot. The valley of <hi>Marmelo</hi> which was the charge of <hi>D. Gaspar de la Cueva</hi> was garrison'd with a good grosse of foot to make opposition against the succour which in their opinion would attempt to enter that way. The quarter of <hi>Cosena</hi> belonged to the Duke of <hi>Ossuna,</hi> who as General of the Horse had the choisest troops with him, though for number they were no more then those in the quarter of <hi>Bargada.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The quarters of St. <hi>Francis</hi> and our Lady of <hi>Grace</hi> were alike manned. The one being the charge of <hi>D. John de Zuinga</hi> son to the Marquis of <hi>Avila fuente,</hi> and the other of Collonel <hi>Martin Sanches Pardo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this order the Enemy lay before the place determining to have the victory by the benefit of time, and without using any approaches or assaults, continually offended it with their Canon, from which no part of the City was secure. And yet the Arms which most afflicted the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seiged were those of Heaven, which scattering abroad with a strange contagion, the malignity of diseases diminished the number of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders so fast, that in fourscore dayes that the seige continued, there dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed betwixt Countrey-men and Souldiers seven thousand persons.</p>
            <p>The want of remedies encreased the danger, the consideration that they were wanting encreased the infirmities. In the Apothecaries shops there were none of those medicines, which experience hath invented a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the violence of diseases. There were no Physicians to be had for the sick, since the Physicians wanted help themselves. There was neither dyet nor nourishment for people in that condition, and the misery had been far greater, but for the providence of the <hi>Conde</hi> General, who continually stole into the town some relief or other of that kind from <hi>Campo major.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Conde</hi> General travail'd in raising the new Army with all heat, and without losing an houres time, or giving himself any ordinary refreshment, there seemed a contention betwixt the fatigues of his body and mind. The advice he had of the condition of the place dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled his cares, which were encreased by the knowledge that the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my every day expected recrutes, wherewith to re-inforce his strength.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:184759:8"/> And understanding most particularly their Forces, and the calamities of the Town, he used so noble a dissimulation to animate his Souldiers, that with great chearfulness he gave it out, that the Army was rather going to a Victory then Relief, since the Enemy had nothing to hope, nor the Town to fear: So well does a great minde in the appearances of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamest danger, know how to triumph over bad fortune. In this Siege there was seen a notable testimony of what the Justice of a Cause can do: for during the time of it, there were above 3000 <hi>Spaniards</hi> who came and rendred themselves voluntarily in several Towns of <hi>Portugal,</hi> and selling their Arms and Horses at the best price, desired Pasports for their own Countrey, from whence they had been forced by violence. This being a rare case, that not mercenary Nations, but the very natural Vassals of a King, should rather go over to the Enemy, then cooperate in an unjust enterprize. And yet there was not one example either in the Town or Army, of any <hi>Portugues</hi> that went over to the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding the many Manifests dispersed through the Camp in which <hi>Don Luis de Haro</hi> tempted the fidelity of the <hi>Portugues</hi> with large and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary promises.</p>
            <p>The success answered the diligence of the <hi>Conde</hi> General; for in the end of <hi>December</hi> there was a new Army formed, if not equal to that of the Enemy, at the least capable to attempt the relieving of the place. In this short time a Train of Artillery was formed, Provisions got together, Carriages mounted, the Souldiers paid, and the Auxiliaries assembled out of the Countries, men saw with their eyes an Army, and with their discourses measured the time, when their judgements suspended betwixt their sense and their reason, would hardly let them believe what their eyes saw. But the power of diligence is not to be measured by the space of the hours, and a great zeal often brings things about in an instant, which are not to be wrought by time.</p>
            <p>At the same time the <hi>Conde</hi> General sent to provide store of Ovens in the Town of <hi>Campo Mayor,</hi> which is three Leagues distant from the City of <hi>Elvas,</hi> whence there were continually Convoys passing, that in case there were occasion, the Army might be provided that way. And at the same time they had others in <hi>Villa Vitiosa, Borba,</hi> and <hi>Estremos,</hi> for the same effect: for though the intent of the General were to succour the place by force, and to break and dislodge the Enemy with his sword in his hand, it was prudence, since the success of War depend up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the providence of God, to be provided against all accidents, in case necessity should advise another way of succour.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Conde</hi> General having thus disposed things according to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctates
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:184759:8"/> of valour and prudence, the 17 of <hi>December</hi> wrote to <hi>D. Sancto Manoel,</hi> Governour of the Town, that for the better effecting of a busi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of that importance, he thought it fit that he should call together all the Commanders that were with him, and take their opinions concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the way and manner of introducing the succour, advertising him particularly of the condition in which the Enemies Army was. The 23<seg rend="sup">d,</seg> the <hi>Conde</hi> General received <hi>D. Sancto Manoels</hi> answer, wherein after he had described the Form, the Fortifications, and the Strength of the Enemies Quarters, he gave an account of the opinion of his Captains, as he was directed, and that by the universal consent of them all, the best way to introduce the Succour, was, for the Army to march with their swords in their hands straight to the Town, by our Lady of <hi>Grace,</hi> leaving the left-hand way; for besides that our Army by that means would march cover'd and defended by the River of <hi>Chinches</hi> on the right hand, till they came under the Artillery of the Town: This was the only way that the Town could assist the Army, which by reason of the smallness of their numbers, could not sally out but under their own Cannon.</p>
            <p>He advertised him that there were various opinions concerning the taking of the Quarter called our Lady of <hi>Grace,</hi> some thinking it not fit to imbarque the Army in it, and that there was nothing to be feared from thence, since by reason of its great height, it could give no considerable offence. And yet the greater number of which, he was one thought it best to send a part of the Army to possess that Post, since by that means it would be impossible for the Enemy to body in that place; and the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voys of <hi>Campo-Major</hi> would be secured in case there were any need of them.</p>
            <p>The 17 of <hi>December</hi> arrived at <hi>Estremos D. Rodrigo de Castro,</hi> Count of <hi>Mesquitella,</hi> whom a great and dangerous sickness could not hinder from coming to exercise his Office of Camp-Master General in so perillous an occasion, and though his countenance and disposition sufficiently disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered the severity of his disease; in the noise of Armes (which are natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral to those who are bred to them) within a few days he was perfectly recovered.</p>
            <p>These informations being come from the Town, which the <hi>Conde</hi> Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral trusted only with himself, he called the chief Captains of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to Counsel, where for the better observing of secrecy, were only pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent, <hi>Andrew Albuquerque</hi> General of the horse, the Count of <hi>Mesquitella</hi> the General of the Artillery, <hi>Alfonso Furtado de Mendosa,</hi> &amp; the <hi>Conde de Feira</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He represented to them the condition of the Enemies Fortifications, and that the importance of <hi>Elvas</hi> would admit no dispute whether they
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:184759:9"/> should put in succour, but only of the way how succour should be put in; and so they should only confer on that which offered it self upon this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular.</p>
            <p>They all agreed unanimously of the same way, which the Captains in the Town had done, in which the <hi>Conde</hi> General acquiesced with great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment, taking this consent of the Captains in both places, for a certain presage of victory, it seeming probable to him, that the judgements of men being so different, this uniformity of opinions could proceed from no other cause then the inspiration of God, upon whom alone depends the felicity of successes.</p>
            <p>The way of putting in the succours being agreed on, there was advice thereof sent to the Governour of the Town, the <hi>Conde</hi> General ordering him to send Guides to conduct the Army that way, advertising him of what was most necessary, that he might be ready. The next days were spent in getting together what was fit for the march of the Army, which was design'd to be the Eleventh of <hi>January,</hi> of which there was advice sent to the Governour of the Town, by three <hi>Courriers,</hi> who were all taken by the Enemy.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Conde</hi> General, by means of <hi>Francisco de Brito,</hi> Governor of <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menha,</hi> who had been General of the Fleets of <hi>Brasile,</hi> had Spies in the Enemies Army in pay, who continually informed him of their Power, and in the beginning of <hi>January</hi> he received advice, that with the great levies which successively came to them, and the Horse which they had in their Garisons, their Army came to Eleven thousand Foot, and 3000 Horse, which did not alter the chearfulness and resolution of the <hi>Conde</hi> General.</p>
            <p>The day design'd was come, when men by their discourses conjectured the success; for the days before being rainy and cloudy, the Sun this morning rose with so much brightness, as if the Spring had been come before its time, to give the <hi>Portugues</hi> Army the welcome of Victory.</p>
            <p>With so chearful and auspicious a presage, the <hi>Conde</hi> General set out of <hi>Estremos,</hi> and mustering his men, as well those who were with him, as those who out of the Garrisons were to joyn with the Army, he found they amounted in all to 8000 Foot, whereof 2500 only were in pay, the rest being Militia men, who with their gallantry and valour, supply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the defects of their number and quality, shewing by the chearfulness of their countenances, that they went rather to conquer then to fight.</p>
            <p>There followed 2000 Baggage horses, which carried Victuals and Ammunition, with 2000 sheep and hoggs to put into the Town, a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:184759:9"/> Carts loaden with Munition Planks, and other implements of War, seven pieces of Artillery, from two to four pound bullets, the condition of the ways not enduring any bigger.</p>
            <p>Who were the chief Commanders of this Army, may be seen in other places as I have had occasion to name them; but here it will be so necessary to particularize every one, that the repetition of them again, can be no fault.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Don Luis de Meneses,</hi> then Count of <hi>Cantanhede,</hi> commanded the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my; Camp-Masters General were <hi>Andrew Albuquerque,</hi> great Constable of <hi>Sintra,</hi> who was also General of the Horse, and <hi>D. Rodrigo de Castro,</hi> Count of <hi>Mesquitella,</hi> and Governor of the Province beyond the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, <hi>Alfonso Furtado de Mendosa,</hi> great Constable of <hi>Covilliana,</hi> General of the Artillery. Lieutenant-Generals of the horse, were <hi>Achim de Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maricourt,</hi> and <hi>Dinis de Mello de Castro,</hi> who were of this Province, <hi>Manoel Freire d' Andrada,</hi> and <hi>Gil Vas Lobo</hi> of the Province of <hi>Beira,</hi> and <hi>Pedro de Lalanda Frances</hi> of the County of <hi>Algarue, John Silva de Sousa,</hi> and <hi>John Vanicheli</hi> were Commissaries.</p>
            <p>The Infantry was divided into 16 Terces or Regiments, of which were Colonels, <hi>Pedro de Mello, D. Manoel Henriques, Anthony Galuano, Ferdinand de Mesquita Pimentel, Bartholmy de Azeuedo Coutinho, Gabriel de Castro Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bosa, Luis de Sousa de Meneses, Luis de Mesquita Pimentel, Alvaro de Azeu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edo Barreto, Antonio de Sa Pereira, Gregory de Castro de Morais, Alfonso de Barros Trouano,</hi> Lieutenant to the Camp-Master-General, commanded the Regiment of <hi>Manoel Velho,</hi> who died at <hi>Estremos;</hi> Captain <hi>Lucas Barrozo Sembrano</hi> commanded the Regiment of <hi>Mertola,</hi> Major <hi>Baltazar de Sa Sotto,</hi> Major of the Regiment of <hi>Moura,</hi> which had belonged to the Baron <hi>de Alvito, Manoel Nunes Leitane,</hi> the Regiment of the <hi>Conde da Torre, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noel de Silua de Orta,</hi> that of <hi>Francisco Pacheco Mascarenhas, Diego Gomes de Figueiredo, Ascenso, Alvares Barreto,</hi> and <hi>Manoel Lobato Pinto</hi> were Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants of the Camp-Master-General.</p>
            <p>Our Army lodged in the field which the people of the Countrey call <hi>Alcaravisa,</hi> near to an Hermitage of our Lady of <hi>Orada,</hi> an ancient Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, which acknowledges for its Founder, the Constable <hi>Nuno Alvares Pereira,</hi> that terror of the <hi>Castillian</hi> Nation, and immortal honour of the <hi>Portugues,</hi> the sight of which, with the memory of him, so spirited our Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, that they seem'd to bespeak the like slaughter to the Enemy, as they had anciently suffered by that Captain in the fields of <hi>Aljubarotta.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here the horse and foot which were in the Towns of <hi>Villa Vitiosa, Bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba,</hi> and <hi>Jerumenha</hi> joyned with the body of the Army, the night following they lodged a league from <hi>Atallaya dos Matos,</hi> nor would they make any
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:184759:10"/> greater march, though the length of the day permitted it, that they might stay for the horse and foot which were to come from <hi>Campo major, Arronches</hi> and <hi>Monforte.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The march continued the third day, and before the Army could reach the fountain <hi>dos Sapateiros</hi> the Enemy sent to discover them from <hi>Atallaya,</hi> which they had possest with a troop of horse, which retired, and with them the Souldiers which garrison'd <hi>Atallaya,</hi> and then the Army advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing up the hill from whence they first discovered the City of <hi>Elvas,</hi> the General of the Artillery by the command of the General saluted the town with all their Artillery, to which they answered with theirs, who confident of their success congratulated one another before the battail with demonstrations that are used in victories.</p>
            <p>The Army marched alwayes within sight of the Enemies quarters, till they took their lodging at the Bishops hill on the other side our Lady of <hi>Grace,</hi> half a league from the town, and not a mile from the Duke of <hi>Ossu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi>'s quarters.</p>
            <p>Then the camp-Master General and General of the horse <hi>Andrew Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buquerque</hi> went in person to view the Enemies lines and fortifications on that side, which he found so much mended, that the most forward cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage might have repented the intention of attempting them. For the next day after the moving of the Army, the Enemy took five men which <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cho Manoel</hi> had sent out of the town as guides to the Army, who being all put to the torture, confess'd, that that was the way the succour was to come, which was the cause that the Enemy with incredible labour had added new fortifications to the first, making the lines higher and the trenches deeper, and fortifying all the way with Estacades, Forts and redoubts. That night the <hi>Conde</hi> General call'd to council all the chiefs of the Army, and proposing to them reasons for the succouring of the town, the consequences that might befall the Kingdome if it were not succour'd, the credit of the Arms of <hi>Portugal,</hi> the expectation of other Nations, and the particular honour of every Captain, it was unanimously agreed to relieve the place what ever came of it, without so much as one vote that considered either the power of the Enemy so much superiour, or the strength of their fortifications. Here the General received a letter from <hi>Francisco de Brito</hi> Governour of <hi>Jerumenha,</hi> who gave him advice, that the night before there were come recruits to the Enemy of 3000 foot and 500 horse, whereby their Army was become so much superiour to ours, that they were 14000 foot and 3500 horse besides the advantage of their forts. And such was the generous courage of the <hi>Conde</hi> General, that he kept this advice to himself without so much as communicating it
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:184759:10"/> to his chief Officers, that he might not alter the resolution which was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in the Council, upon which depended the saving of the place, whose danger was so pressing, that it was necessary to make use of violent means, even though they appear'd desperate.</p>
            <p>There is a report that the chiefs of the Enemies Army were in Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil the day before, and that it being the General opinion of them all, that they should receive our Army without their trenches, or at least by the side of them, <hi>Don Luis de Haro</hi> resolv'd the contrary, thinking it im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possible, that he being in person with an Army in every respect superiour to that which the Duke of St. <hi>German</hi> had at the siege of <hi>Olivenza,</hi> the present power of <hi>Portugal</hi> inferiour in number and quality to that which was to relieve that place should have the courage to assault the trenches, which in that occasion they had no mind to do. So usual is it with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine providence to corrupt the judgements of those, whose fortune it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to change.</p>
            <p>The night was wholly spent in disquieting the Enemy, and giving them continual alarms, and notwithstanding the rigour of the season, in the whole army there was not a tent set up more then the Pavilion where the Council met.</p>
            <p>The morning of the 14. of <hi>January</hi> was come, which will be a day of festivity to <hi>Portugal</hi> in future ages, but overcast with thick clouds, as if Heaven had been unwilling to behold the slaughter of so many Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, of which those fields this day were to be the theatre, and happening to be upon a Tuseday, which is superstitiously fear'd and fatal to the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily of <hi>Meneses,</hi> of which the <hi>Conde</hi> General was chief, his valour over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came the auguries of his name, and the fatality of the day, making it the most fortunate of all the year in the Calendar of <hi>Portugal.</hi> The felicity of this day began with the presence of all the Army at the holy sacrifice of the Altar.</p>
            <p>The Enemy passed all the night in great care, standing continually in <hi>Battalia,</hi> and at break of day sent to discry our army by <hi>D. John Pacheco</hi> Lieutenant General of the horse with four troops, who seeing the stilness and quiet of the <hi>Portugues</hi> army, which was occasioned by the thickness of the clouds, concluded there would be no battail that day, and so assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the rest of the Captains, who being of the same opinion, drew off the souldiers, who mann'd the lines, into their quarters, leaving only the forts which defended them garrison'd.</p>
            <p>It was now six of clock in the morning, when, as the prologue to those generous and admirable actions which the <hi>Portugues</hi> perform'd that day, the army of <hi>Portugal</hi> began to move slowly from the quarter where it was
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:184759:11"/> lodged against the trenches of the Enemy, and to put it self in <hi>Battalia</hi> before them.</p>
            <p>Before the Vant-guard as Lieutenant of the Camp-master General was <hi>Diego Gomes de Figueiredo,</hi> five Sergeant Majors, and a thousand foot selected out of the whole Army to give the assault, divided into five bodies, some arm'd with Pistols, Partisans, Swords and Bucklers, and Firelances, others with Musquets, who carried bavins and spades to fill the ditches. Every one of these bodies was commanded by one of the Sergeant-majors, who were <hi>John Machado Fagundes, Antonio Tauares de Costa, Fernando Martins de Seixas, Alvaro Saraiua, &amp; Anthony Vascon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellos de Mendosa.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Vant-guard was commanded by <hi>D. Rodrigo de Castro</hi> Count of <hi>Mesquitella,</hi> with whom was the General of the Artillery <hi>Alfonso Furtado de Mendosa.</hi> It consisted of 3000 foot in five squadrons, of which were Collonels <hi>Pedro de Mello, Emanuel Henriques, Antonio Galvano, Fernando Mesquita,</hi> and <hi>Bartolomeo Azeuedo:</hi> in the right wing was <hi>Pedro de Mello,</hi> next to him <hi>D. Emanuel Henriques,</hi> the left wing was commanded by <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonio Galvano,</hi> the next place by <hi>Bartolomeo Azeuedo,</hi> the middle by <hi>Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nando Mesquita.</hi> They were flank'd with 16 Battaglions of horse, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisting of somewhat above a thousand, in the head of whom marched the General of the horse <hi>Andrew Albuquerque.</hi> The Lieutenant Generals of that Province <hi>Achim de Tamaracourt,</hi> and <hi>Denis de Mello de Castro</hi> with the commissaries <hi>John Silva de Souza,</hi> and <hi>John Vanicheli</hi> commanding them.</p>
            <p>The main Battail consisted of 2000 foot in six squadrons, which were form'd out of the Regiments of <hi>Antonio sa de Pereira, Luis de Sousa de Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neses, Alfonso de Barros Trovano,</hi> and out of the Regiments of the Count <hi>da Torre, Francisco Pacheco,</hi> and <hi>de Moura,</hi> which were commanded by their respective Sergeant-majors <hi>Emanoel Nunes Leitano, Emanuel de Silva Dorta</hi> and <hi>Balthezar de sà Sottomajor.</hi> The Count of <hi>Torre</hi> was in the right wing, next to him <hi>Luis de Sousa,</hi> and then <hi>Alfonso de Barros.</hi> In the left wing was the Regiment of <hi>Moura,</hi> next to that the Regiment of <hi>Antonio de sa,</hi> and then that of <hi>Francisco Pacheco.</hi> They were flank'd with 16. Battailons of about 900 horse with the Lieutenant Generals <hi>Gil Vas Lobo</hi> in the right wing, and <hi>Emanuel de Andrada</hi> in the left.</p>
            <p>The Rear-guard was composed of 2000 foot in five squadrons, with the Collonels <hi>Gabriel de Castro, Luis de Mesquita, Alvaro de Azeuedo, Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry de Castro,</hi> and <hi>Luke Barrozo.</hi> In the right wing marched <hi>Gregory de Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stro,</hi> next him <hi>Alvaro de Azeuedo,</hi> in the left wing <hi>Gabriel de Castro,</hi> who was followed by <hi>Luis de Mesquita,</hi> and in the middle was <hi>Luke Barrozo.</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:184759:11"/> They were flank'd with eight Battallions consisting of 800. horse under the command of Lieutenant General <hi>Pedro de Lalanda.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Baggage followed with the succours, but the Artillery could not march with the Army by reason of the wayes which hindred it; and yet it happened to be of great use in the battail, for is was left upon a hill, from whence it did considerable damage to the Enemy, when the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral of it <hi>Alfonso Furtado de Mendosa</hi> had taken order for accommodating and securing it, he went himself into the Vant-guard to assist the Count of <hi>Mesquitella</hi> Camp-master General.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Conde</hi> General was in the body of the main battail, but in the time of fight he kept no certain place, that he might give direction where, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as the accidents of the day required. He was accompanied by the Count of <hi>Feira Garcia de Mello</hi> great huntsman of the Kingdome, <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stopher de Mello</hi> son and heir of the great <hi>Porter, Gonsalo Pires, Emanuel de Andrada</hi> Governour of the town of <hi>Peniche,</hi> and of the frontieres of <hi>Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res Vedras,</hi> and <hi>Leiria</hi> in the Province of <hi>Estremadura,</hi> Captain <hi>Michael Alvares Galvano</hi> Governour of fort St. <hi>Anthony,</hi> Captain <hi>Mathias Correa</hi> Lieutenant to the Camp-master General <hi>Emanuel Pinto,</hi> and the compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of guards, of which were Captains <hi>Cesar de Meneses</hi> and <hi>Andrew Gatino.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>D. Sancho Manoel</hi> Governour of the town, understanding that the fight would be at break of day, placed the night before in the <hi>Cover'd way</hi> Collonel <hi>Diego Gomes de Figueiredo,</hi> and <hi>Simon Correa de Silva,</hi> and the Count of St. <hi>John</hi> with 450 musquitiers, which were all the men they could make that were able to fight, and in the morning commanded Commissary <hi>John de Silva</hi> to sally into the field with 170 horse, with whom went the Count <hi>de Torre,</hi> though he were sick, having no Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his own, and <hi>Fernando de Silveyra.</hi> The Commissary had order to fall upon the Enemy as soon as the battail begun, that he might weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en them by diversion, and the Collonels were commanded not to pass the river <hi>Seto,</hi> but to employ themselves only in such occasions as the fortune of war should offer them there. And on that side where the <hi>Portugues</hi> Army was to fall on, he planted 20 pieces of Artillery of several diame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tres under the charge of <hi>Peter James Magellan.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this order our Army advanced against the fortifications of the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and as the distance was but small from the place we lodged to their lines, the <hi>Spanish</hi> Captains perceiving our designe, call'd back their men in all haste, whom they had drawn to their quarters, out of a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swasion that we would not assault them, of which their Lieutenant Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral <hi>Don John Pacheco</hi> had been the cause. The haste they were in was
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:184759:12"/> the reason that they changed their orders, their infantry placing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves in one front without any depth defended by their lines. Behind their foot stood a Batallion of 800 horse with the Duke of <hi>Ossuna</hi> their General, that they might dissipate our men, who charged their lines (in case they entred) before they could form themselves into a body, and before the Town stood another Batallion of 800 horse under the command of the Commissary General <hi>Quintanales,</hi> that the rest of their men might securely employ themselves in the battail without being infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted in their backs by the sallies of the besieged.</p>
            <p>Now were the minds of the <hi>Portugues</hi> so elevated, that they could hardly contain themselves within their ranks, all of them desiring the signal of battail, when the <hi>Conde</hi> General with a presence so chearful as almost infused an assurance of victory, remembred every one of the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligations of his birth and loyalty, <hi>That these were the same Enemies over whom they and their Ancestors had so often triumph'd, that the presence of the Favourite &amp; Nobility of</hi> Spain <hi>might make the victory more glorious, but not more dangerous, that the Enemy contended for our servitude, we for our liberty; that betwixt two such motives that must be most powerfull which concerned ones own preservation. That their glory consisted in our ruin, their gain in our destruction. That those Forts which they had raised upon our land, would rather be monuments of our glory then impediments to our victory; that they were men brought together by force and violence, we out of love and for our own defence. That their minds might easily be conjectured by the numbers of them which had yielded themselves to us, that they who had done so were the bravest of their men, &amp; therefore had the boldness to leave them, that they who stayed behind were detained by their fear and not their courage. That in the Town our wives, our children, our brethren, and our kindred called to us, whose redemption depended upon this succour in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, the love and preservation of our King, whose fate was involved in this success, in the world the glory of the Kingdome, in which we were born, which would either be won or lost in this battail. Lastly, things were come to that pass, that as to conquer or to dye was the most honourable choise for the valiant, so it was the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest for the fearful, and therefore as they entred into the battail they should remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber their Ancestors and have a care of their Posterity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A painter of Antiquity having undertaken to draw the beauty of a hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then goddess, covered the face with a vail, for judiciously foreseeing that art could not reach the reality, he would have it understood, that that which would be wronged with the faintness of colours could only be preserved in the profundity of shadowes. Pens astonished and elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence confounded would pass in silence the relation of the battail, for no stile being able to arrive to the truth, it will be best, that that which
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:184759:12"/> must needs suffer diminution by the touches of a pen, should be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serv'd entire in astonishment and admiration. It is certain, that that which cannot be greater when it is done, must appear less when it is written.</p>
            <p>'Twas now nine a clock when our Army approached the enemies Lines, betwixt the Quarters of our Lady of <hi>Grace,</hi> and St. <hi>Francis,</hi> being flank'd on the right side with the River <hi>Chinches,</hi> at which time the clouds began to dissipate, that Heaven might be witness of that contest be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the two most valiant and warlike Nations of <hi>Europe,</hi> of which that Field was to be the Theatre.</p>
            <p>The Artillery of the Army play'd without intermission, and that in the Town discharged upon the enemy, when the <hi>Portugues</hi> after they had received three Volleys of Spanish musquets, throwing down the Bavins which they had to facilitate their passage, with incredible resolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion assaulted the enemies Lines, and putting the Defenders to the sword, broke them down, and entred them with so equal fury, that none was second, nor none was first.</p>
            <p>The horse were so brave, that they would not stay till the foot had made them a breach to enter, but breaking down the Works them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, there joyntly entred into the Trenches, with them the Lieutenant General <hi>Denis de Mello, Achim de Tamaracourt,</hi> and <hi>Gil Vas Lobo,</hi> and <hi>Manoel Freire,</hi> All of them trampling and cutting down such as resist<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with so brave an emulation, that this admirable action being the work both of the Companies and Troops, it could not be decided whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had the better title to the Victory.</p>
            <p>The enemies Trenches being entred, the Spanish horse charged the Regiments of <hi>Antonio Galvano,</hi> and <hi>Bartholameo de Azeuedo</hi> (who were both wounded) with intention to break them before they should be form'd into a body; but they were prevented by Commissary <hi>John de Silva,</hi> who fell in with them, and began a furious skirmish, out of which went wounded the Count of <hi>Torre,</hi> who, his horse being killed, had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibly been taken prisoner, but that he was reliev'd first by his own courage, and then by another horse which was presented him by a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate souldier.</p>
            <p>In this encounter was <hi>Ferdinand da Silveyra,</hi> of his Majesties Councel of War, a son of the house of <hi>Sarzedas,</hi> who in his youth served and had charges in the Wars of <hi>Flanders, Italy</hi> and <hi>Brasile,</hi> but in <hi>Portugal</hi> had no other but Admiral of the Navy Royal, by reason of a troublesome accident he had, which some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times took away the use of his reason, depriving him of the service of his Prince, and the Kingdom of so great a Captain. But that impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diment
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:184759:13"/> was not sufficient to keep him from assisting at the siege of <hi>Bada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jos,</hi> following the generous inclinations of his courage, which was the most prevailing passion in him. The same impulsion which brought him from the Court to the Army, drew him out of the Town into the field, where fighting valiantly he shewed, though he was not the man he had been, he was still a Souldier, till enraged at the resistance he met with, he threw himself amongst the enemy to kill and die, that the world might see, though fortune had kept him from serving his Prince in his life, she could not keep him from serving his Countrey in his death.</p>
            <p>The Lieutenant General <hi>Denis de Mello,</hi> who had entred the Trenches with the Battalions of the left wing which he commanded, briskly charged those of the Duke of <hi>Ossuna</hi> the General of the enemies horse. At the same time the Infantry stormed the Forts, which obstinately de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended themselves, and the Colonels <hi>Simon Correa,</hi> and the Count of St. <hi>John</hi> exceeding their orders, or interpreting them other then they were given, passing over the River of <hi>Seto,</hi> imbodied with those who were breaking down the Lines, and after joyned with them who stormed the Quarter of our Lady of <hi>Grace;</hi> so that in all parts there was a furious and obstinate battail.</p>
            <p>In the mean time the <hi>Conde</hi> General went about with singular courage, animating sometimes one, sometimes another, so proud to see the chief Commanders, Officers and Souldiers do so bravely, that desiring out of an honorable emulation, rather to be their companion then Leader, he often forgot of what importance the life of a General is in such occasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <p>The Camp-master-General Count <hi>Mesquitella,</hi> who went from place to place giving direction, as long as the battail lasted, and the General of the Artillery, who was incessantly employed, seeing they had not yet taken any one fort of the enemies, without which there was no se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing their success, commanded Colonel <hi>Alvaro de Azevedo</hi> to assault a fort of the enemies, which bravely defended it self, who marching thither with his Regiment, tearing up the Palissadoes with their hands, and fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the ditches with them, scaled the works, and put the defenders to the sword with so singular a courage, that the Count <hi>Mesquitella</hi> was so taken with it, that he was pleas'd to honor the combat with his sword, and entring with it in his hand into the Fort, shewed that the charge of Camp-master-General had not made him forget the boldness of a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Souldier.</p>
            <p>The enemy still continued fighting about the Lines of Circumvallati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:184759:13"/> and form'd another Line as it were of Countervallation of that side; when the General of the horse, <hi>Andrew Albuquerque</hi> seeing a Regiment of Auxiliaries, of which <hi>Luis de Sousa</hi> was Colonel, lose ground, he cast himself amongst the Souldiers, making them turn again by his example; when it pleasing Heaven to sell the victory to the <hi>Portugal</hi> at so dear a price, or (which is more likely) it being now time to reward his rare vertues with the immortal felicities of a better life, a musquet bullet hit him, which passing through his Arms, shot him through the breast, he remaining unmoveable for a little time, as if that great minde had been loath to leave the battail before the victory.</p>
            <p>He was a Gentleman of extraordinary endowments of body and minde, of a chearful presence, a sweet conversation, affable in discourse, discreet, without malice, valiant without noise, vertuous without hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crisy, a religious observer of Military discipline, of great entireness in matters of Justice, of singular constancy in good and evil fortune. He made himself loved, he made himself feared; but in gaining mens af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections he never employed Caresses, nor securing himself by fear, made use of punishments. He disposed things with sweetness, he did his business without noise, &amp; executed it with felicity. Valour in him was rather natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral then acquired, he being always master of his mind in the greatest dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, so that that seems to some to be insensibility in him, which indeed was constancy. The service of his King was his life &amp; his delight; yet in nineteen years time he was only twice at Court. He was a Souldier, a Captain, a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonel, a General of the Artillery, a General of the Horse, and Camp-master-General, being always as great a subject as a chief; none knew better to obey, none knew better to command: In a word, he was a Gentleman in all respects so great, that the 14. of <hi>January,</hi> it being the most auspicious day to future ages that is in the Calendar of <hi>Portugal,</hi> will be likewise the most lamentable for his memory.</p>
            <p>Colonel <hi>Luis de Sousa</hi> was likewise shot in his left side with a musquet bullet, of which he died, his hasty death preventing those applauses and rewards which were due to his most qualified deserts.</p>
            <p>When the battail began, <hi>Pedro de Meneses, Andrew Gatino</hi> Captains of the Guard to the <hi>Conde</hi> General, begg'd his leave that they might go help their companions, and coming to the Fort which <hi>Pedro de Mello</hi> stormed, they valiantly encountred a body of the enemy which was coming to charge, and though the meeting cost the life of <hi>Andrew Gatino,</hi> who fell valiantly fighting, <hi>Pedro Meneses</hi> revenged him with the death of above fourscore Spaniards, which he cut the throats of, putting the rest to flight.</p>
            <p>Now the resistance of the Spaniard by little and little declined, and victory began to declare her self for the Arms of <hi>Portugal,</hi> for the horse with whom Lieutenant General <hi>Denis de Mello,</hi> and <hi>Don John de Silva <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:184759:14"/> Luis de Haro,</hi> who thought the houses of <hi>Badajos</hi> more secure then the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifications of his Trenches, accompanied with a few horse, brought to <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dajos</hi> the news of their misfortune before three a clock in the afternoon. The foot which did not flie so soon, made good their forts, for though some of them were yielded up, the others still resisted.</p>
            <p>At this time, as the fight continued still in the Forts, the <hi>Conde</hi> General advanced with the succours in spight of the bullets, which without inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission crossed the way where he marched, and entring within the Lines, put it into the Town; at the sight of which the besieged revived, and congra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulating with acclamations of joy, those first signs of their redemption, gave thanks to God for that glorious and wonderful success which he had given to the Arms of <hi>Portugal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At the time that the succour was put into the Town, the <hi>Conde</hi> General met at the River <hi>Seto,</hi> with the Governor <hi>D. Sancho Manoel,</hi> who leaving the Town to the care of the General of the Artillery, <hi>Pedro Magalhan</hi> was sallied out with <hi>D. Luis d' Almeida</hi> and 20 horse, and after he had given the <hi>Conde</hi> the salutation of victory, he marched to that part where <hi>Pedro de Mello</hi> fought.</p>
            <p>Still the enemy fought obstinately in one fort, the furthest to the right side of the line, which was the most capacious of all, &amp; contained the best men of the Spanish Army, where Col. <hi>Pedro de Mello</hi> who scaled it, fought most part of the day at the expence of many lives of the defendants and assail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants. And in the fort of our Lady of <hi>Grace</hi> continued the same resistance in spight of the storms and attempts which were made by Col. <hi>Correa da Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>va,</hi> and the Count of St. <hi>John,</hi> who retired wounded, being driven off with baggs of powder, which the defendants set on fire.</p>
            <p>The night parted the contest, and though to open and free the way to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Portugal,</hi> it was necessary to get these Forts, it seeming a thing im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possible to obtain them in the darkness of the night, the fight was deferr'd till the next day, the conquering Army lodging under the walls of the town with their front toward the quarters of our Lady of <hi>Grace</hi> and the <hi>Bargada,</hi> and the <hi>Conde</hi> General quartered in the Hermitage of St. <hi>Laza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> without the town.</p>
            <p>Singular and mighty would be the glory of <hi>Portugal</hi> in the world, if the Nations who inhabit it had been present at the rare and prodigious acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of valour which were performed that day. Courage, boldness, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solution was equal in all, some had the better fortune of having occasion to shew it. To particularize some, were odious, to relate what all did, impossible, and in case it were not, who could be named first without justly offending the second, who as well deserved to be first? The field afforded room for all men to doe alike, since they were all engaged at the same time. But it is not so in the order of writing, for there i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:184759:14"/>
            <p>The stone in which the great <hi>Alphonso D. Albuquerque</hi> caus'd to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graven the names of those Captains who behaved themselves bravely in the conquest of the City of <hi>Malaca</hi> may be an example for writers, who relate the actions of the <hi>Portugues.</hi> For that famous General seeing them discontented, whose names he intended to eternize, because he had put one first, another second, as it was necessary in the order of writing them to do, he commanded the stone which had the names in it, and stood over the gate of the Fort which he had built, to be taken out, and turning the writing inwards, engraved on the outside of the stone those words of the 117. <hi>Psalm, Lapidem, quem reprobaverunt aedificantes.</hi> Besides it is not my intent to inform <hi>Portugal</hi> what the <hi>Portugues</hi> did, but to inform the world what was done by <hi>Portugal.</hi> The actions of those who behav'd themselves bravely are sufficiently known in our own Kingdome. The pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick conscience is the best Register of them; all tongues celebrate them, all men admire them, and the munificence with which his Majesty will reward them will make known every mans deservings. I relate the success, and praise only the dead, since envy will spare none who are alive.</p>
            <p>All that night the Army stood in <hi>Battaglia,</hi> intending the next morning to assault the Enemy in the quarter, where they were fortified, and as soon as it was break of day the <hi>Conde</hi> General marched with the Army towards the quarter of <hi>la Corte,</hi> which he found as full of munition as it was empty of men. For fear had so possest the conquer'd, that in the obscurity of the night they quitted their quarters in such haste, that they durst not stay to carry away the Cabinet of the favourite, in which were found letters from the K. that discovered all the secrets of the Monarchy.</p>
            <p>The Horse presently march'd down to the River of <hi>Caja</hi> with the Camp-master General <hi>D. Sancho Manoel,</hi> where though they overtook the reer of the Enemy as they were flying over the water, they contented them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves having such a number of Prisoners already to let them pass leaving their persons free, and taking from them only a piece of Cannon which they were drawing off; the Souldiers enriching themselves with the spoils of the Duke of <hi>Ossuna</hi>'s baggage.</p>
            <p>The Camp-masters <hi>Don John de Zuinga,</hi> and <hi>Don Nicholas</hi> of <hi>Cordova,</hi> who defended the Forts of our Lady of <hi>Grace</hi> and the <hi>Rozario,</hi> and the day before had made a brave resistence in hope that by the favour of the night approaching they should receive orders from their chiefs, either for their defence or their retreat, seeing themselves frustrated of their expectation, and the hazard of their condition rendred themselves up with 600 foot to the mercy of the conquerours.</p>
            <p>Such was the fear and terrour the conquer'd conceiv'd at our victory, that coming to <hi>Badajos</hi> they presently fell a breaking down the fortificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which the <hi>Portugues</hi> had left when they rose from the siege, being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:184759:15"/> they might return again to take up their quarters there, and obtain the town, so terrified and astonished with that rout and slaughter.</p>
            <p>The loss of the <hi>Spaniards</hi> was one of the greatest, that till that day the Monarchy had ever suffered. For their Army consisting of 14000 foot, and 3500 horse in the muster at <hi>Badajos,</hi> after the rout arriv'd only to 5000 foot, and 1500 horse, all the rest were wounded, dead, pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soners, or fled. But in respect of the circumstances it was the greatest, for the prisoners all agreed, that at the first marching of that Army there were 28000 foot, and 8000 horse, of all which only those few relicks were remaining.</p>
            <p>The field was covered with carkasses, amongst which were many of the chief commanders, Collonels, Lieutenant-Generals, Lieutenant-Collonels, Commissaries of horse, Sergeant-majors, Captains of horse and foot, which with the Gentlemen and Reformado's exceeded the number of 3000. The prisoners were as many or more then the slain, and of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ame condition and quality, some <hi>Titulati,</hi> and many sons and brothers of the Titular houses of <hi>Spain,</hi> besides 600 sick and wounded, which the <hi>Conde</hi> General sent to <hi>Badajos.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They lost 17 pieces of Canon, 5 Petards, 3 Morter-pieces, all the train <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f Artillery, many Ensignes, 15000 Arms, &amp; all the provision and ammu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ition which were got together to support the Army and furnish the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>owns. Lastly, their whole quarters with their richest baggage, which the <hi>Conde</hi> General gave as a spoil to his Souldiers.</p>
            <p>Of the <hi>Portugues</hi> there dyed only the General of the horse <hi>Andrew Albuquerque,</hi> the Admiral <hi>Ferdinand de Silveira,</hi> Collonel <hi>Luis de Sousa,</hi> who went off wounded, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd died afterwards. Two Captains of horse, ten Captains of foot, two Adjutants, ten Ensignes, four Sergeants and 177. common Souldiers. There went off wounded the Count of St. <hi>John,</hi> the Count <hi>de Torre Simon Correa da Silva, Bartholomao de Azu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edo,</hi> and <hi>Antonio Galvano</hi> Lieutenant to the Camp-master General <hi>Ascenso Alvares,</hi> four Sergeant-majors, one Adjutant of a Lieutenant, 23. Captains, 8. Adjutants, 22. Ensignes, 32. Sergeants, and 592. common Souldiers.</p>
            <p>The news of the victory arriv'd at <hi>Lisbone</hi> the 16. of <hi>January,</hi> at the same time that King <hi>Alfonso</hi>'s Majesty was present at the anniversary solemnity of the holy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament in the Parish Church of St. <hi>Engratia,</hi> this being the first time that he had shew'd himself in publick to his people; circumstanc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s which prognosticate the great and reiterated felicities which it is to be hoped our Lord God will grant to his auspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious government. And father <hi>Prospero dos Martyres</hi> of the religion of the Regular Canons of St. <hi>Augustine,</hi> promising in his Sermon good news from the Army of <hi>Alen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ojo,</hi> the Post came in, the Letters were read, and then the solemn hymn of <hi>Te Deum Laudamus</hi> being sung, the Sermon continued, which being begun in prayers ended in thanks, which his Majesty, the Nobility of the Court, and the People with festival demonstrations gave to God, who is the only Lord of Hosts and Victories.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:184759:15"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="fre" type="genealogy">
            <pb facs="tcp:184759:16"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:184759:16"/>
            <head>Genealogie des Roys de Portugal.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>EMANVEL ROY DE PORTVGAL PREMIER de ce nom, qui succeda au Roy Iean le second son Cousin germain, ou qui plustost a este faict Roy par election du peuple, eut trois femmes:</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>1. Isabelle,</hi> fille de Ferdinand &amp; Jsabelle Roy &amp; Royne de Castille, dont il eut vn seul filz nom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mé Michel, qui mourut en son ieune aagé.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>2. Marie,</hi> seur de sa premiere femme, dont l eut neuf enfans.
<list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>1. Iohan le troisiéme,</hi> qui fut successeur du Royaume, &amp; eut pour femme Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terine fille de Philippe premier de ce nom Roy de Castille, Archiduc d' Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strice &amp;c. dont (estans tous les autres morts en leur enfance,) il retint,
<list>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Marie,</hi> laquelle espou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sa Philippe lors Prince &amp; a present Roy de Castille, dont fut en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendré Charles Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce dudit Castille, le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quel (comme le bruict en est constant) le pere auroit faict mourir en la prison.</item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Iean,</hi> Prince de Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugal, qui espousa Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hanne fille de l' Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pereur Charles, dont a esté procreé le Roy Sebastien, qui succe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da a son ayeul pater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel en la Couronne, &amp; mourut à l'age de <hi>24.</hi> ans en Afrique.</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>2. Isabelle,</hi> la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quelle espou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sa l' Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reur Charles le <hi>v.</hi> dōt sont yssus
<list>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Philippe II<seg rend="sup">e</seg>. de</hi> ce nom Roy de Castille.</item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Marie,</hi> qu'espousa l' Empereur Maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milien <hi>2<seg rend="sup">e</seg>.</hi> de ce nom</item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Iehanne,</hi> laquelle se maria auec Iehan Prince de portugal</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>3. Beatrix,</hi> laque<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> espousa Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les Duc de Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoye, desquel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> a este eng<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                              <desc>•••</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <list>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Emanuel Philibert,</hi> qui a laissé vn filz vnique Duc de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                                    <desc>••</desc>
                                 </gap>
                                 <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uoye à present.</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>4. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>douic,</hi> qui <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>retement, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>uoit espou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se vne fille <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>mmée Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>te, dont a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>sté procreé.
<list>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>DON ANTONIO.</hi>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>5. Ferdinand,</hi> le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quel espousa la fille du Conte de Marialua, dōt il eut deux filz qui mou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurent du vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant de pere &amp; mere.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>6. Alfonse,</hi> qui fut fait Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>7. Henry,</hi> qui fut aussi fait Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puis Roy, par la mort du Roy Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bastien.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>8. Edouard,</hi> qui espou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sa Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dose Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chesse de Bargançe, don sont este pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creéz
<list>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Marie,</hi> qu'espousa Alexandre Prince de Parma, dont sont yssus trois enfans</item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Caterine,</hi> laquelle se maria auec le Duc de Bergançe.</item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Edouart,</hi> qui morut sans est re marié.</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>9. Antoine,</hi> qui mou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rut en son enfance.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>3. Eleonor,</hi> seur de l' Empereur Charles le quint, dont il eut vn filz nommé Charles, qui trespassa en son enfance, &amp; Marie laquelle mourut sans estre mariée.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:184759:17"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:184759:17"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>